Arthur Henry Pierce Papers, 1900-1914
Smith College Archives
Arthur Henry Pierce Papers
1900-1914
Pierce, Arthur Henry, 1867-1914
RG 42 UUID:ae9b325d-34d0-4373-be5a-33bd67519c51
5 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of psychology. Contains research, lecture notes, and photographs.
Arthur Henry Pierce was born July 30, 1867. He received his undergraduate degree from Amherst College in 1888 and then left for Europe on a fellowship for seven years. Harvard awarded him a doctorate in 1899 and he joined the faculty of Smith College in 1900 as a Professor of Psychology. His research focused on perception and the senses, which was the topic of his book Studies in Space Perception published in 1901 by Longmans, Green and Co. Arthur Pierce was also an avid outdoorsman, often going on trips into the woods via canoe, motor or on foot. He died unmarried in Northampton, MA on February 20, 1914 of pneumonia.
This collection consists primarily of the research and lecture notes created by Arthur Henry Pierce during his tenure as a professor of Psychology at Smith College. The collection contains very little biographical or personal information. There are five photographs that show him standing on the Smith College campus, wearing rain gear and holding oars in preparation for an excursion and in formal portraits.
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Arthur Henry Pierce papers were donated to the College Archives from a number of sources.
- General c.1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Notes c.1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Publications - "An Appeal from the Prevailing Doctrine of a Detached Subconsciousness" reprinted from the Studies in Philosophy and Psychology, commemorative volume dedicated to Prof. Charles E. Garman of Amherst College, Houghton Mifflin Co. undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Publications - Studies in Perception, New York: Longmans, Green and Co. 1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notes on Geometrical Illusions Vol. 1-3 c.1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notes on Laboratory Techniques Vol. 4 c.1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Advertisements c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Affective states c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Aphasia c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - Apperception c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - Association c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - Association of Diagnosis c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Attention c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Auditory Space Perception c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - The Blind c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Color Blindness c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Complication Experiments c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Lecture Notes - Criminal Psychology c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Lecture Notes - Drugs and Alcohol c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Lecture Notes - Emotions c.1900-1914 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Lecture Notes - Fatigue c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Fusion c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Habit c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - History of Psychology c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - Images c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - Inhibitions c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Instincts c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Intellectual Processes c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - Memory c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Mental Tests c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Perception c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Lecture Notes - Porgandoff Illusion c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Lecture Notes - Pleasure and Pain c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Lecture Notes - Psychology of Advertising c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Lecture Notes - Psychology of Testimony c.1900-1914 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Lecture Notes - Philosophy 12 - Experimental Psychology 1907-1908 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Lecture Notes - Reading process c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Lecture Notes - Reasoning c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Lecture Notes - Sensation c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Lecture Notes - The Senses of Sight, Hearing, etc. c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Lecture Notes - The Soul c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Lecture Notes - Suggestion c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes - Synaesthesia c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Lecture Notes - Telepathy c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Lecture Notes - Visual Space Perception c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Lecture Notes - Weber's Law c.1900-1914 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Research on Apparent from of the heavens, etc c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Data c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Experiments c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Notes c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Original Records c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Questionnaires c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Reviews c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Student observations c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Summaries c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Size Illusion of Celestial Magnitude Vol. 1-2 c.1900-1914 (Box 5, Folder 11)